http://www.chatteris.org/safeguarding-and-privacy-policy

Safeguarding & Privacy Policy
SAFEGUARDING CONTACTSIf you have information about a safeguarding situation where a child or adult is in immediate danger, or requires immediate medical attention, call the emergency services on 999. Do not delay.The safeguarding team in Chatteris is committed to helping you create protective and supportive environments where all people, and especially those who may be vulnerable, are able to worship and pursue their faith journey in safety.We follow the national legal and procedural framework for safeguarding children and adults, and Church of England policy and practice.Juliette Brown: Chatteris Parish Safeguarding Officer (PSO) and Church WardenE | juliette@chatteris.org
T | 07989 470064Rebecca Wagg: Chatteris Parish Safeguarding Administrator (police checks and training)E | rebecca@chatteris.org
T | 07886 847071Rev.d Canon Wendy Thomson: Vicar of Chatteris Parish ChurchE | wendy@chatteris.org
T | 01354 692173Diocese of Ely Safeguarding Officer - Rebecca Boswell, Duty Phone 01353 652747 National Church of England Safeguarding Website - please follow the link below: https://www.churchofengland.org/safeguarding/promoting-safer-church-safeguardingPCC PoliciesThe PCC have posted Policies, including Policies for (1) Safeguarding and (2) Privacy. Please contact a Church Warden or the Operations Manager if you would like to see more of our policies.1. Safeguarding PolicyPROMOTING A SAFER CHURCHThe Parochial Church Council of St Peter & St Paul’s Church, ChatterisThe following policy was agreed at the Parochial Church Council (PCC) meeting held on 29th May 2019.  In accordance with the National House of Bishop’s Safeguarding Policy for the Church of England, our church is committed to:Promoting a safer environment and culture.Safely recruiting and supporting all those with any responsibility related to children, young people and vulnerable adults within the churchResponding promptly to every safeguarding concern or allegation.Caring pastorally for victims/survivors of abuse and other affected persons.Caring pastorally for those who are the subject of concerns or allegations of abuse and other affected personsResponding to those that may pose a present risk to others. The Parish will:  Have a named Parish Safeguarding Officer (PSO) to work with the incumbent and the PCC to implement policy and procedures. Adopt zero tolerance to inappropriate behaviour and bullying, by ensuring that all incidents are recorded and promptly reported to the PSO or incumbent. Safely recruit, train and support all those with any responsibility for people to have the confidence and skills to recognise and respond to abuse. Ensure that refresher training takes place every three years Display in church premises and on the Parish website the details of who to contact if there are safeguarding concerns or support needs Listen to and take seriously all those who disclose abuse. Take steps to protect children and adults when a safeguarding concern of any kind arises, following House of Bishops guidance, including notifying the Diocesan Safeguarding Adviser (DSA). Offer support to victims/survivors of abuse regardless of when it occurred. Care for and monitor any member of the church community who may pose a risk to children and adults whilst maintaining appropriate confidentiality and the safety of all parties Ensure that health and safety policy, procedures and risk assessments are in place and that these are reviewed annually. Review the implementation of the Safeguarding Policy, Procedures and Practices annually.If you have information about a safeguarding situation where a child or adult is in immediate danger, or requires immediate medical attention, call the emergency services on 999. Do not delay.The safeguarding team in Chatteris is committed to helping you create protective and supportive environments where all people, and especially those who may be vulnerable, are able to worship and pursue their faith journey in safety.Juliette Brown 07989470064
- Chatteris Parish Safeguarding Officer & Church WardenRevd Canon Wendy Thomson 01354 692173 - vicar Rebecca Wagg rebecca@chatteris.org - Parish Safeguarding Administrator for support for police checks and trainingDiocese of Ely Safeguarding Duty Phone
01353 652747 2. PrivacyThe Law is changing and it requires us to be transparent about how people’s personal data is being used. As a church we use your personal data in a number of ways.This Privacy Notice explains what to expect when Chatteris Parish Church collects and uses your personal data.PERSONAL DATA – WHAT IS IT?Personal data is information about a living individual which is capable of identifying that individual.  It might include information such as title, name, and address, date of birth, email and telephone number.OUR PROMISE We are committed to respecting your privacy and ensuring that the personal data you have entrusted us with is kept safe and processed only for the purposes declared. We will always treat any sensitive personal data with the greatest of care. We will never share your data with third parties outside of the parish without your explicit consent unless we are legally required to do soWHAT WE USE YOUR DATA FORWe collect your personal data for various reasons at various times and may be used for any of the following:To inform you of news, events, activities and services running at Chatteris Parish Church;To enable us to provide a voluntary service for the benefit of the Parish;To provide necessary pastoral care if you are seeking assistance as required;To administer membership and attendance records according to our Safeguarding Policy;To maintain parish registers for the Church of England; such as baptisms, weddings, and funerals;To fundraise and promote the interests of Chatteris Parish;To manage our employees and volunteers;To maintain our accounts and finances, including the processing of gift aid applications;YOUR RIGHTS Unless there is a greater legal duty, you have the following rightsTo request a copy of the personal data we hold about you.To request that any incorrect data is corrected.To request that any data is deleted where it is no longer necessary to keep such data.To object to your data being used, and ask us to stop.The right to lodge a complaint with the Information Commissioners Office.THE LAW We can only process your data if we have a legal basis for doing so, and we do.As a not-for-profit religious organisation we can process personal data for the purposes specified providing you are a member, previous member or have regular contact; and that we do not disclose your information to any third party without your consent.It is deemed a legitimate activity to process your data in order to continue to be an active Christian presence, supporting you and the local community in this place.[1]It is necessary to process your data in order to provide you with a service and ongoing support. For example as a result of baptism, wedding or funeral ministryWe have a legal duty to process data as an employer and as a church reliant on volunteers.HOW LONG WE KEEP YOUR DATAWe will only keep your personal data for as long as it is required, after which time, your data is destroyed. Gift Aid, financial records and attendance records are kept for six years. Electoral role membership is renewed every five years. Parish Registers are kept permanently for all Baptisms, Weddings and Funerals.REPORTING CONCERNSPlease contact the Vicar if you wish to raise a concern about our handling of your personal data.Vicar:              Revd Canon Wendy Thomson                        The Vicarage, Church Lane, Chatteris, PE16 6JA                        Tel: 01354 692173[1] Details about retention periods can currently be found in the Record Management Guides located on the Church of England website at: - https://www.churchofengland.org/more/libraries-and-archives/records-management-guides
